A Guide to the Rockefeller family Associates, Berent Friele papers FA468
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Business, Corporate, and Political Files, 4; 4.27 Cubic Feet 10 letter document boxes and 1 legal document box
  - Center for Latin American Relations and Americas Foundation, 1977-1981 (Box 11, Folder 164)
    Correspondence, news, and meeting minutes concerning a variety of organizations with focuses on US-Latin American relations. Contains newspaper clippings and a speech made by David Rockefeller at one of these meetings.
  - Chilean Boycott, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 165)
    Includes letters from Peter Grace, an American industrialist, multi-millionaire, owner of the United Fruit Company, and Chairman of the AIFLD (American Institute of Free Labor Development), to Friele.
  - Christiania General Insurance, 1952-1954 (Box 11, Folder 166)
    Contains meeting minutes for the directors of the Christiania General Insurance Corporation, of which Berent Friele was one, as well as financial statements and budget expenditures.
  - Claude C. Erb and Institute of Inter-American Affairs, 1982-1984 (Box 11, Folder 167)
    Correspondence with an associate of Berent Friele's called Claude Erb as well as other correspondence regarding Erb's dissertation on US-Latin American Relations and Nelson's involvement. Includes newspaper clippings a many postcards and handwritten notes.
  - Claude Erb and David Rockefeller, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 168)
    Contains a few letters of correspondence written among Claude Erb, David Rockefeller, and Berent Friele concerning Claude's research on Nelson Rockefeller's contributions to US-Latin American relations.
  - Coffee, 1950-1952 (Box 11, Folder 169)
    Contains memorandums and correspondence on the production of soluble coffee in Latin America and investment opportunities for the International Basic Economy Corporation. Includes newspaper articles and a pamphlets with details of the coffee industry and its place in the Latin American economy.
  - Commission on US-Brazilian Relations, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 170)
    A large compilation of documents, correspondence, and files relating to US-Brazilian relations. Contains newspaper clippings as well as statistics and facts about recent developments in cooperation between the nations. Notably contains a lengthy Harvard University report on nuclear proliferation and Brazil.
  - Correspondence on US-Brazilian Relations, 1976-1979 (Box 12, Folder 171)
    Concerns issues which had arisen straining relations between the US and Brazil mainly centered on disagreements over Brazil's moving towards nuclear technology. Includes newspaper clippings and data analysis. Also includes economic report on Brazil as produced by Wells Fargo Bank N.A.
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1952-1953 (Box 12, Folder 172)
    Contains a memorandum discussing the findings of the Council on Foreign relations on political unrest in Latin America, its causes, how it affects US interests, and suggested courses of action towards it. Contains meeting minutes for the council as they discuss their various perspectives on how to approach investment in Latin America given the current political atmosphere. Contains descriptive individual dossiers on several Latin American countries. Heavy focus on preventing spread of communism.
  - Council on Foreign Relations Brazil Meeting, 1978-1980 (Box 12, Folder 173)
    Contains a published report by the Center of Brazilian Studies at The Johns Hopkins University on developments in Brazil as well as a large photograph addressed to Berent Friele. Includes numerous facts and figures as well as memorandums on the state of the Brazilian economy, especially in regard to an energy crisis.
    - Council on Foreign Relations Brazil Meeting: Photographs, 1978-1980 (Box 19, Folder 258)
  - Council on Foreign Relations US-Brazil Conference, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 174)
    Contains correspondence with Winston Lord, President of the Council on Foreign Relations, in regards to a meeting hosted by the council on Brazil's future role in international affairs. Also contains a pamphlet on the subject.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R), 1972 (Box 12, Folder 175)
    Contains a long document detailing D&R's preliminary reports and progress on development of the Brazilian interior.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R): Brazil Trip, 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 176)
    Contains correspondence by David E. Lilienthal with various Brazilian politicians involved in the development of the country's interior, primarily concerning Brazil's energy crisis and possible trade for oil and natural gas from Iran. Also concerns information on official visits to Brazil by David Lilienthal as well as Henry Kissinger. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R): Brazil Visit, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 177)
    Contains information on visit of David E. Lilienthal to Brazil including documents and itineraries. Also contains large document explaining programs and objectives of the Brazilian Ministry of the Interior as well as documents regarding the promotion of development in the Sao Francisco Region of Brazil. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R): Correspondence, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 178)
    Further correspondence between Berent Friele and David E. Lilienthal with some reference to the increasing displacement of indigenous peoples and destruction of environments in the region of the Amazon Basin. Contains David Lilienthal's resume as well as many handwritten notes. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R) in Brazil and Iran, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 179)
    Correspondence, reports, and data relating to the activities of the D&R Corporation in both Brazil and Iran, mainly involved in surveying regions for creating the best possible developments in oil and nuclear energy. Contains newspaper clippings and letters from both Berent Friele and David E. Lilienthal.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R): Institutional Aspects, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 180)
    Contains a lengthy letter memorandum from David E. Lilienthal of the D&R Corporation to the Brazilian Minister of Interior Jos Costa Cavalcanti concerning development of the SFV (Sao Francisco Valley).
  - David E. Lilienthal and Berent Friele, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 181)
    Contains correspondence between Berent Friele and David Lilienthal regarding Brazil as well as an article which offers a commentary on the development of Brazil's agricultural program. Contains documents and National Geographic maps of the region being developed, as well as all of South America.
  - David E. Lilienthal Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 182)
    Letters and messages primarily between Berent Friele and one David E. Lilienthal, founder of the D&R (Development and Resources) Corporation, concerning energy development in Brazil. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - David Rockefeller and Brazil, 1970-1979 (Box 13, Folder 183)
    Includes magazine article with a brief biography of David Rockefeller, an interview with him, and several photos of him.
  - David Rockefeller and Fazenda Bodoquena, 1970-1979 (Box 13, Folder 184)
    Includes information from stockholder meeting on Fazenda Bodoquena, a large cattle farm in Brazil. Contains balance sheets and financial statements.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R): Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 185)
    Further correspondence between Berent Friele and David E. Lilienthal, as well as other associaties, concerning current projects undertaken by the D&R Corporation in Brazil. Contains newspaper clippings as well as several business reports. Also includes a packet titled "Unifed Development Plan for the Sao Francisco Valley", a business and goal outline.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R): Correspondence, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 186)
    Further D&R relaed material on nuclear energy in Brazil with inclusion of technical data and reports. Contains correspondence with one Henry Maksoud, a notable Brazilian businessman as well as newspaper clippings.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R): Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 13, Folder 187)
    Further correspondence between Berent Friele and David E. Lilienthal regarding matters related to the D&R Corporation. Contains newspaper clippings and a magazine feature on David Lilienthal's life.
  - Development and Resources Corporation (D&R) in Brazil, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 188)
    Materials related to the D&R Corporation in Brazil as well as current events in the Brazilian political world such as the rise to power of General Ernesto Geisel and his closest advisors including Golbery do Couto e Silva. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Energy Crisis, 1972-1977 (Box 13, Folder 189)
    Includes proposal by Rodman Rockefeller detailing his vision for increasing energy independence in the Western Hemisphere utilizing coal, citing the US and Brazil as the two major economic powers and consumers in the hemisphere. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Establishment of Investment Bank in Brazil and IBEC, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 190)
    A large and elaborate report compiled by management consulting firm McKinsey & Company for Chase Bank on the founding and establishment of an investment bank in Brazil as well as initial findings. Contains a selection of charts, figures, and statements.
  - Financial Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 13, Folder 191)
    Details of a visit to Brazil taken by Berent Friele and his correspondence with Nelson Rockefeller. Primarily concerns financial details of the trip.
  - Gould Contract, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 192)
    Documents and correspondence relating to the Gould Paper Company, a paper mill based in the US which was considered for purchase by IBEC to help stave off the shortage of newsprint in Brazil at the time.
  - Gould Paper Company, 1951-1953 (Box 14, Folder 193)
    Further correspondence and files relating to Berent Friele's dealings with the Gould Paper Company, primarily concerning prices of paper sold by the ton and issues over delivery and sale. Much correspondence concerns growing issues between companies Tor Janer and Gould Paper. Includes a lengthy memorandum to the board of directors of the Gould Paper Company. Contains many telegrams and newspaper clippings.
  - Gould Paper Company, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 194)
    Further correspondence and files relating to Berent Friele's dealings with the Gould Paper Company, primarily concerning prices of paper sold by the ton and issues over delivery and sale. Includes many reports of financial statements and stock prices for the company as well as contractual agreements among one Tor Janer, IBEC, and the Gould Paper Company itself.
  - IBEC, 1974-1976 (Box 14, Folder 195)
    Contains letters, messages, and correspondence to and from Berent Friele primarily of a business nature and relating to IBEC (International Basic Economy Corporation). Includes a multitude of articles and papers with information of the internal workings of organizations Berent Friele cooperated with.
  - IBEC Info, 1974-1976 (Box 14, Folder 196)
    Several news articles focusing on IBEC, a Rockefeller company. Contains newspaper clippings as well as a large informational pamphlet for the organization Agroceres.
  - IBEC Research, 1951-1952 (Box 14, Folder 197)
    Includes a proposed agenda for IBEC in improving coffee processing in Brazil. Contains a budget sheet for the proposed studies as well as newspaper clippings.
  - IBEC Research Institute, 1951-1952 (Box 14, Folder 198)
    Assortment of documents and correspondence regarding IBEC and its failed deal to join forces with a company called Anderson, Clayton & Cia which would have funded IBEC's "basic horticultural research program in coffee".
  - Indussa Corporation, 1951-1954 (Box 14, Folder 199)
    A compilation of meeting minutes and financial statements for the Indussa Corporation for which Berent Friele was a director. Also contains a portfolio of stockholders and the stock price and capitalization of stock in Indussa corporation.
  - Interamericana Plax, 1951-1953 (Box 14, Folder 200)
    Contains documents relating to IBEC's involvement in the Brazilian Plastics Project or Plax do Brasil, including financial statements and projected earnings. Also contains earnings and financial statement for Emhart Manufacturing Company.
  - Inter-American Council, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 201)
    Contains memorandums and bulletins by the Inter-American Council of Commerce and Production focusing on the investment interests of various companies and nationalities in the Republics of Latin America. Includes assorted listings of these countries and their primary investments in the countries of Latin America. Includes pamphlets.
  - Investment Bank and Cimento Aratu, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 202)
    Contains estimated profits and sales for Cimento Aratu, S.A., a cement company established by investors of the Interamericana Corporation. Includes memorandum on company financing. Includes a map of Brazil and important areas of the cement industry there.
  - IRI Research Institute, 1974-1978 (Box 15, Folder 203)
    Meeting notes for IRI Council. Projected income sheets for different industries. Balance sheet, income statement, etc. for IRI.
  - IRI Research Institute, 1974-1978 (Box 15, Folder 204)
    Meeting notes for IRI Board of Directors. Information regarding an IRI project based in Oman and correspondence relating to it. Several photos in project outline. IRI research findings on effects of liming and fertilizing several crops on Campo Cerrado Soils.
  - IRI Research Institute Progress Report, 1974-1978 (Box 15, Folder 205)
    Binder which details the agricultural projects undertaken by IRI and planned initiatives.
  - Janer, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 206)
    Includes a summary of Janer orders for paper from the Gould Paper Company. Also includes a letter from the Gould Paper Compant to Janer critical of Janer's failure to comply with their contractual agreements and defaulting on payments.
  - Latin America "Negligence", 1975 (Box 15, Folder 207)
    An assortment of correspondences and articles regarding "neglected" US relations with the Latin American countries. Includes large portrait-style photograph of Nelson A. Rockefeller and newspaper clippings. Also includes Department of State release expressing the US Government's regret at a postponed meeting of foreign ministers by the Argentinean Government.
    - Latin America "Negligence": Photographs, 1975 (Box 19, Folder 259)
  - Latin American Affairs, 1974 (Box 15, Folder 208)
    Correspondence and files relating to US foreign policy towards Latin America, especially in regards to Cuba. Many materials focusing on OAS (Organization of American States). Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Latin American Boycotts, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 209)
    Further correspondence regarding the labor boycotts taking place throughout Latin America. Includes statistics on treatment of trade union leaders and rights in many countries with particular interest in Chile. Includes newspaper clippings and mentions David Rockefeller in a pamphlet regarding the Meeting of the Council of the Americas.
  - Medici Visit, 1969-1973 (Box 15, Folder 210)
    Contains itinerary for state visit of Brazilian President Emlio Mdici to the United States.
  - Mesbla S.A. and Luiz La Saigne, 1952-1954 (Box 15, Folder 211)
    An assortment of correspondence and fact sheets focusing on the profits and financials of Meslba S.A. primarily with one Luiz La Saigne, a Brazilian businessman.
  - National Foreign Trade Council, 1952-1953 (Box 15, Folder 212)
    Documents and correspondence on the affairs of the National Foreign Trade Council primarily concerning US investments in Brazil, but also including other Latin American countries. Includes statistics and charts. Includes copies of Latin American governments' bills establishing the powers of government over trade.
  - New Business Committee, 1951-1952 (Box 15, Folder 213)
    Includes memorandum for IBEC's New Business Committee which focuses on new projects in developing countries such as establishing factories and encouraging new investments. Also includes proposals for short-term financing from IBEC to new companies in Brazil in which IBEC is interested in financing. Includes special memorandum on how to address problem of shortage of newsprint in Latin America.
  - Nelson Rockefeller and Bolivia, 1956-1963 (Box 15, Folder 214)
    Press and correspondence concerning US-Bolivian relations, particularly regarding the visit of the Bolivian ambassador to the United States as well as the re-election of Bolivian President Victor Paz Estenssoro. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - New York University Brazilian Institute, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 215)
    Pertains to a conference held at New York University on matters of US-Brazilian interests. Includes a pamphlet briefing on the history of US-Brazilian relations as well as important facts about Brazil's economy.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 216)
    A compilation of newspaper clippings relating to foreign investment in Brazil and import/export trade.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1954-1956 (Box 16, Folder 217)
    Contains a large compilation of newspaper clippings, regarding current events and relations between the United States and Brazil. Contains several photographs of Berent Friele himself.
  - Northeastern Brazil Drought, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 218)
    Contains correspondence, news bulletins, and documents concerning a drought in northeastern Brazil and its detrimental effects on the people there. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Oivind Lorentzen, 1952-1954 (Box 16, Folder 219)
    Correspondence and documents relating to Oivind Lorentzen, a Norwegian shipping company, named eponymously for its founder, with large amounts of business in shipping to and from Latin American countries, particularly Brazil. Primarily concerning factories to be built in Brazil for oil refinement. Many documents written in Brazilian Portuguese. Contains newspaper clippings.
  - Official Dinners and Luncheons, 1961-1969 (Box 16, Folder 220)
    An assortment of invitations, guest-lists, and itineraries for various official dinners and luncheons held by organizations associated with Berent Friele. Includes a couple of extravagantly decorated dinner invitations, notably one to a dinner in honor of Crown Prince Harald V of Norway.
  - Organization of American States, 1972-1981 (Box 16, Folder 221)
    Correspondence between Berent Friele and other associates of the OAS, particularly Galo Plaza, regarding the activities and goals of the organization.
  - Organization Survey of Tenco, Inc., 1959 (Box 16, Folder 222)
    A report compiled by management consulting firm Booz Allen & Hamilton for the president of Tenco, Inc. on the organization of the corporation and how to promote further efficiency through reorganization. Includes an independent letter addressed in part to Berent Friele which determines the corporation chooses to accept the proposals outlined in the report. Contains facts and statistics.
  - Preliminary Study for Aracruz Celulose, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 223)
    A large bound memorandum for the company Aracruz Celulose composed by engineering consulting company Jaakko Poyry & Co. The report details the future plans of the company to create a plant in Brazil specializing in making pulp from eucalyptus trees. Contains many profit sheets and financial statements.
  - President-Elect Costa e Silva and Brazilian Congressional Group New York Visit, 1960-1967 (Box 16, Folder 224)
    Details of President-Elect Costa e Silva's 1967 visit to New York as well as the Brazilian Congressional Group's 1963 visit. Includes itineraries and correspondence.
  - Press, 1951-1954 (Box 16, Folder 225)
    A large compilation of press articles relating to Latin American affairs pertaining to the doings of Berent Friele and IBEC. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Proposal to Minister of Interior of Brazil for Consulting Services, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 226)
    A memorandum by the D&R (Development and Resources Corporation) containing proposed action to be undertaken by the Brazilian Government in developing the resources of the Sao Francisco Valley Region.
  - Relatorio Da Comissao Brasiliero-Americana de Producao de Generos Alimenticios, 1942-1944 (Box 20, Folder 227A)
    Contains reports on the activities of the Comissao Brasiliero-Americana de Producao de Generos Alimenticios agency of the Brazilian Ministry of Agriculure for Nelson Rockefeller as president of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (CIAA) and Dr. Apolonio Sales as Minister of Agriculture for Brazil. Contains photographs of people involved in project as well as statistics and statements.
  - Relatorio Da Comissao Brasiliero-Americana de Producao de Generos Alimenticios, 1942-1944 (Box 20, Folder 227B)
  - Rockefeller Mission to Brazil, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 228)
    A massive compilation files documenting a great variety of statistics and facts about Brazil as well as information on a presidential mission to Brazil.
  - Rockefeller Mission to Latin America, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 229)
    Contains documents pertaining to the Rockefeller Mission to Latin America, most notably a letter from President Richard Nixon thanking Berent Friele for his contributions to the mission. Includes newspaper clippings and pamphlet entitled "The Vision Letter" with details of the Rockefeller Report on Latin America.
  - Rodman C. Rockefeller, 1972-1977 (Box 17, Folder 230)
    Includes memos and messages, usually to Rodman Rockefeller from Friele, regarding agricultural research and its potential practical applications in Brazil by virtue of the International Basic Economy Corporation, of which Rodman was Vice President. Includes newspaper clippings and letters in Brazilian Portuguese.
  - Rodman Rockefeller's Schedule, 1972-1977 (Box 17, Folder 231)
    Outline of Rodman Rockefeller's itinerary with many meetings with Brazilian notables.
  - Rodman Rockefeller Visit to Brazil, 1972-1977 (Box 17, Folder 232)
    Correspondence letters detailing Rodman Rockefeller's travels to Brazil and communication with Friele expressing enthusiasm for continuing Rockefeller family interest in bettering US-Brazilian relations into the next generation. Also includes some itineraries from the trip and a sketch of a ?population pyramid' outlining the research being performed by the RCR Group in Brazil on population demographics.
  - Rodman Rockefeller Visit to Brazil Clips, 1972-1977 (Box 17, Folder 233)
    Articles and newspaper clippings, mostly in Brazilian Portuguese, related to Rodman Rockefeller's visit to Brazil including his meeting with Brazilian President Emlio Mdici.
  - Scandinavian Airlines System (SAS), 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 234)
    Correspondence, meeting notes, and other material relating to Scandinavian Airlines System (SAS), on which Berent Friele was a member of the board of directors. Includes several pamphlets and published reports detailing the logistics and financial statements of the corporation. Includes photographs of airline directors and planes.
  - Ski for Light Materials, 1976-1977 (Box 17, Folder 235)
    Pamphlets and advertisements for the Ski for Light Program. Includes many pictures of program in magazine.
  - Sulfur, 1951 (Box 17, Folder 236)
    Contains a multitude of newspaper clippings and a handwritten memo on production of sulfur in Brazil.
  - Summary of Findings and Recommendations of IBEC, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 237)